"Micromorts: How Risky Is
It to Go Under Anesthesia?"
Hundreds of millions of operations
are performed every year,
and the risk of death is
typically around a half a percent,
to which patients might say things like,
“I could die just as
easily crossing the road,”
making it clear they
really don’t understand
the difference in magnitude of risk.
One way to communicate
risk is by analogy.
For example, just going
under anesthetic carries about
a 1 in 100,000 chance you won’t
wake up. How much is that?
Well, that’s about the same
risk as an expert sky dive.
Okay, but that still may be kind
of hard to wrap your head around.
It's hard to think in
terms of small numbers.
Imagine discussing a
0.0017 mile x 0.00227 mile rug.
How big even is that?
We need more digestible units.
Enter the micromort
as a unit of comparing
and communicating risk to patients.
A micromort is a unit equivalent to
one in a million chance of dying.
One in a million is like
the chances of ﬂipping a coin
and getting 20 heads or tails in a row,
or a little less than the
chances of getting a royal flush.
But the real utility is to help
compare different risks to one another,
using the same metric.
For example, driving a
hundred miles entails about
a one in a million chance of
death, so that’s one micromort.
Scuba diving is like
five micromorts per dive;
so, each dive is as risky
as driving 500 miles.
So, now we have a way to
directly compare the risk
of surgical procedures
and common activities.
Giving birth is as risky as driving
from NY to LA and then back again,
but getting a cesarean is
more than twice as risky.
Even something like a simple hernia
repair carries the same risk
of dying as like sky diving 200 times.
Now obviously, sometimes
you have no choice,
but death from varicose vein
surgery or circumcision
could probably be avoided.
I was surprised to learn
that regular horseback riding
is like four times deadlier
than rock climbing,
but getting chemo and radiation
for head and neck cancer
is riskier than rock-
climbing for 500 years,
driving 5 million miles, or
jumping 5,000 sky dives, etc.
One leading cause of death
I really didn’t talk about
in How Not to Die is
accidental death.
We have approximately a one
in a million chance of dying
just by accident every day of our lives,
and about half of that risk
is dying in a car crash,
based on U.S. averages.
Then, there are all sorts of other ways.
I am surprised to learn Americans
have about a 1 in 200,000 chance
every year of dying from a
foreign body entering an orifice
other than the mouth.
Other things we may want to avoid
include climbing Mount Everest,
about 30 times riskier than
coal mining or base jumping.
Trains and planes are actually
equivalent over the same distance,
but riding a motorcycle is about 50 times
deadlier than riding in a car,
though cycling to a
destination is riskier too,
about 10 times as deadly
as driving in the near term.
Here’s a good example of how one
can use micromort comparisons
to help put things in perspective.
Certain types of breast implants
can cause a rare type of cancer,
a type of breast implant-
associated lymphoma.
You can imagine how scary this is
for the millions of women
who have implants,
but check out the risk compared to
the risk of other common activities.
Your risk of dying from
this kind of cancer is less
than a single day of skiing.
Now, it’s probably better to
die quick on the slopes
than all the slow suffering of cancer,
and risk of bankrupting your family,
but at least it can put the
risk of the implant-cancer
killing you in context.